<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD DocBk XML V3.1.4//EN"
                         "http://nwalsh.com/docbook/xml/3.1.4/db3xml.dtd">

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="db2xhtml/xsl/main.xsl" ?>

<article>
  <title>initiumpsalmi.rb</title>
  <subtitle>tool to make a notated first verse of a psalm</subtitle>
  
  <articleinfo>
    <author>
      <firstname>Jakub</firstname>
      <surname>Pavlík</surname>
      <email>jkb.pavlik@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
  </articleinfo>

  <para>
    initiumpsalmi.rb is a simple Ruby script
    created to make typesetting of office chant books a bit more comfortable.
    One of the least entertaining works in the course of such a book
    preparation is, to set the first verse of each psalm to the psalm
    tone which should be used. 
    (Experienced chanters don't need this, but the choir I prepare books
    for stays always open for total newbies and needs thus this feature.)
    So I automated the work. 
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>Prerequisites</title>

    <simplelist>
      <member>Ruby 1.9.*</member>
    </simplelist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Invocation</title>

    <synopsis>
      <command>ruby initiumpsalmi.rb</command> 
      <filename>psalmfile.pslm</filename>
      <filename>psalmtonefile.gabc</filename>
      <optional>
	<filename>outputfile.gabc</filename>
      </optional>
    </synopsis>

    <para>
      The command takes two to three arguments - the third one is 
      optional. All must be valid file names.
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  psalm-file - text of the psalm in a special format 
	  I use to generate pointed texts (see below)
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  psalm-tone-file - psalm tone to be used - a valid 
	  <application>Gregorio</application> input with special
	  formatting (see below)
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  output-file - where to write the output; if no output
	  file is given, the script selects an output file name
	  itself; if a dash is given, the output is printed
	  to the standard output.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Known bugs</title>

    <para>
      If any of the input files is malformed in any way, the script behaves
      in an unexpectable way and sometimes crashes, sometimes produces malformed
      output.
      I'm not going to work too hard to improve it, because the script
      is just a helper tool in my own workflow, not intended to be
      offered to anyone else. Anyone interested may use it too,
      but on his/her own risk. Having any problems with it, just e-mail me.
    </para>
    <para>
      Some less typical psalmodic formulas (like the termination I.D2
      or the mediation of mode III) aren't supported.
      (Don't know yet if I want to work on this.)
    </para>
    <para>
      Psalm verses with flex aren't supported. (I want to fix this one day.)
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Psalm file (*.pslm) format</title>

    <para>
      A psalm file is a plain text file.
    </para>
    <para>
      It's first line is considered a title and thus ignored by our script.
    </para>
    <para>
      The second line is also ignored, it is usually empty.
      (To make the title stand out.)
    </para>
    <para>
      Any line beginning with # is ignored.
      When anywhere on a line # appears, it is ignored as well as anything
      comming after it.
      (System of comments similar to that of Ruby and some other
      programming languages.)
    </para>
    <para>
      The first not ignored non-empty line is considered beginning of
      the first verse. (And the first verse is the only one 
      our script is interested in.)
    </para>
    <para>
      Each psalm verse usually has two parts:
      first and second halfverse. (Some verses may have three parts.
      Bad news: these are not supported yet.) Like this:      
    </para>
    <blockquote>
      <para>
	Dixit Dóminus Dómino meo: * Sede a dextris meis:
      </para>
    </blockquote>
    <para>
      In the psalm file each of them needs to be on it's own line
      and the first one must end with a space followed by an asterisk.
      Like this:
    </para>
    <programlisting>Dixit Dóminus Dómino meo: * 
Sede a dextris meis:</programlisting>
    <para>
      Accented syllables (one to two per part of the verse) important for the
      psalm tone are to be enclosed in square brackets.
    </para>
    <programlisting>Dixit Dóminus [Dó]mino [me]o: * 
Sede a [dex]tris [me]is:</programlisting>
    <para>
      And - in the first verse only, for the needs of our script -
      all the other syllables need to be divided by slashes:
    </para>
    <programlisting>Di/xit Dó/mi/nus [Dó]mi/no [me]o: * 
Se/de a [dex]tris [me]is:</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Psalm tone file (*.gabc) format</title>

    <para>
      Psalm tone file is, on the first place, a valid 
      <application>Gregorio</application> GABC input file.
      (On Gregorio and GABC see 
      <ulink url="http://home.gna.org/gregorio/">Gregorio homepage</ulink>.)
    </para>
    <para>
      <application>initiumpsalmi.rb</application> ignores the header
      of the GABC file. However, it is very strict in expectations
      concerning the musical content following the header.
    </para>
    <programlisting>initial-style: 0;
%%

(c4)
(g) (h) (j)
(j) (jr1) (hr0) (h.)  (,)
(j) (kr1) (jr0) (j.) (:)
(j) (i) (j) (hr1) (gr0) (g.) (::)</programlisting>
    <para>
      (Valid psalm tone file for tone VIII.G)
    </para>
    <para>
      Any empty lines at the beginning of the music part are ignored.
    </para>
    <para>
      The first non-empty line (here line 4) is expected to contain key
      information.
    </para>
    <para>
      The second, flex tone. (Not supported yet, so, ignored for now.)
    </para>
    <para>
      The third line, tone of the first halfverse. The first note
      is recitation note and will be repeated as many times as needed.
      Note with flag r1 is accented note, note with flag r0 is "cave note"
      (only used when needed).
      There may be up to two accentuated notes per verse and each has to be
      followed by two notes - one "cave" note and one normal note.
    </para>
    <para>
      The fourth line contains tone of the second halfverse,
      the rules are the same as for the first halfverse.
    </para>
  </section>

</article>